Benjamin Ward

Email: Phone: LinkedIn:

Github: Website: benjamin.e.ward@outlook.com (256) 566-5467

<u>linkedin.com/in/benjamineward</u> <u>github.com/BenjaminEllisWard</u>

https://builtbybenward.com



PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Software engineer focused on web development with experience in both government and private industry. Adapts quickly to new environments and challenges. Acknowledged by superiors as a hardworker who brings value to an organization through technical knowledge and ability to learn new systems. Dedicates a high level of focus to projects from beginning stages until completion.

EXPERIENCE

SOFTWARE ENGINEER - Daxko / Birmingham, AL / 2019 - 2020

- Developed a custom, in-house CRM app. Worked across the full-stack including a React front-end, .NET app layer, with relational and doc db's.
- Integrated CRM app with **Twilio's SMS API**, allowing users to craft and automate text messaging to reach customers. Developed the SMS text creation/reporting Ul's, API integration, and data capture.
- Participated in an agile environment. Contributed to stand-ups, ticket grooming meetings, planning sessions, and retros. Presented and demoed new development to external teams during sprint reviews.
- Additional projects included API development (with exposures to third parties) and a mobile app.

.NET DEVELOPER - 4M Research Inc. / Huntsville, AL / 2018 - 2019

 Contributed to the development of several enterprise web applications for a DoD customer. Applications featured **n-tier** architecture, **EF** data access, **MVC** UI layer.



- Deployed code to testing, staging, and production environments.
 Experience developing on network servers through a virtual machine.
- Served as the point of contact for all things related to Fortify, the organization's security-oriented static code analyzer.
- Co-authored organization's guidelines for compliance with Defense Information Systems Agency (DISA) mandated security criteria.

COMBAT MEDIC – US Army – 82nd Airborne Division / Ft. Bragg, NC / 2015 - 2019

- Provided emergency medical interventions as a first responder for more than 100 high-risk training events.
- AIRBORNE
- Performed physical examinations and presented findings to medical provider in a clinical setting. Assisted with minor surgeries.
- Was the primary authority on medical supplies and equipment for the organization. Managed inventory of medical equipment with a personal responsibility of more than \$1M.
- Jumped out of planes.

SKILLS

- ♦: Strong suit!
- : Experienced
- : Comfortable
- Learning now

Front End

- **♦**React
- Javascript
- HTML/CSS
- Npm/webpack/babel
- Bootstrap
- Typescript

Back End

- **♦**C#
- .NET (Core & Framework)
- **&**ASP.NET MVC
- T-SQL
- Dependency Injection
- ORM's (Dapper/EF)
- NServiceBus

Hosting/Db's

- SOL Server
- IIS
- AWS: EC2/RDS
- RavenDb
- Windows Server

Disciplines

- REST API Development
- Mobile responsive design
- X-browser design
- TDD

PROJECTS

Personal Site – https://builtbybenward.com

- Website that I began developing in April 2020 to demonstrate my experience with web development.
- ASP.NET MVC app with React front end. Communicates with a separate .NET Core Web API / SQL Server for data persistence. A separate API is more than this site needs; I expanded the system arbitrarily for demonstration purposes to resemble a **microservice architecture**.



- I recently migrated portions of the site to **Typescript** just to learn a new js flavor. Also introduced **Redux** and migrated from Bootstrap 3 to **Bootstrap 4**.
- Hosted on **AWS** with **EC2** Windows Server and a SQL Server RDS.
- Additional front-end technologies include: styled-components, React-Bootstrap, sass/scss.
- Planned future work: **Improve Lighthouse** score and introduce Material UI.

Daxko Engage - https://www.daxko.com/solutions/engage

- A custom, in-house CRM tailored for nonprofit fitness and community centers. Main project during time at Daxko.
- Integrated with other Daxko applications as well as third party web API's. Personally contributed to integration with Twilio's SMS API. Delivered automated texting feature MVP and deployed to production.

twilio-split-sms - https://www.npmjs.com/package/twilio-split-sms

- Minor project I undertook to solve billing calculation related to sms texting.
- Based on text messages' internal segment splitting related to GSM encoding.
- Specifically, this package accounts for Twilio-specific smart encoded characters in addition to the GSM charset.
- The basis of this package was forked from codesleuth's <u>original split-sms repo.</u>

EDUCATION

B.S. HEALTHCARE ADMINISTRATION (2018)





MICROSOFT SYSTEMS AND SOFTWARE ACADEMY (MSSA) (2018)



This program is sponsored by Microsoft to equip selected veterans with the knowledge and skills necessary for a career in programming. Technical instruction is delivered through accredited college courses by Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University. Curriculum includes:

- C#, T-SQL, ASP.NET MVC, cloud computing, Azure Cloud Platform, and other .NET technologies
- Visual Studio, SQL Server
- Experience with industry best-practices such as source-control (git) and test-driven development
- Team-based development
- Experience working with Scrum/Kanban methodologies
- Unit and integration testing
- Experience developing on the full stack, culminating in an individual project where the candidate plans, designs, implements, tests, and deploys his/her own custom web application

